Guide to the Massachusetts Railroads Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Massachusetts railroads collection
1822-1909
MS 971
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
(1 box, 1 folio)
Correspondence, financial and legal documents, maps, schedules, and newspaper clippings from the records of various Massachusetts railroads eventually incorporated by lease or merger into the Boston and Maine Railroad or the New York Central Railroad.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Massachusetts Railroads Collection consists of correspondence and papers, 1822-1909, of various Massachusetts railroads eventually incorporated by lease or merger into the Boston and Maine Railroad or the New York Central Railroad. The Nashua and Lowell Railroad pooled facilities with the Boston and Lowell Railroad in 1857-1878 and was leased by the latter in 1880. The Boston and Lowell Railroad was leased to the Boston and Maine Railroad in 1887. The Boston and Worcester consolidated with the Western Railroad in 1867 to form the Boston and Albany Railroad, the last named acquiring the Grand Junction Railroad and Depot Company in 1868. In 1900 the Boston and Albany was leased to the New York Central Railroad.
Papers of the Boston and Lowell Railroad, 1822-1882, include a history of the title of Lechmers Point Flats for right of way along the Merrimack River, minutes of directors' meetings, contracts, petitions, lists of shareholders, and a small amount of correspondence. Persons represented here are Patrick Jackson, 1780-1857, first treasurer, Charles Storrow, 1809-1904, civil engineer and general manager for ten years, and George Stark, manager for twenty years.
Papers for the Nashua and Lowell Railroad from March and April of 1839 include lawyers' briefs, testimony, evidence, etc., in the case of Nashua and Lowell versus Boston and Lowell, involving the right of the Massachusetts government to prescribe the toll paid by the former railroad to the latter for the joint use of its facilities. The lawyer for the Boston and Lowell Railroad was R. R. Nichols, and for the Nashua and Lowell Railroad, Peleg Sprague, 1793-1880, the famous Massachusetts jurist.
Papers of the Boston and Albany Railroad include those collected by Ebenezer Baldwin relative to the prospect for a railroad, 1828-1829, and papers from 1851-1909, which include memos of bills payable and receivable, records of incoming freight, balance sheets, cash collection, and correspondence.
Papers of the Grand Junction Railroad and Depot Company, 1859-1869, include fire insurance policies, bids and estimates for wharf repairs, a drawing of a plan for the Grand Junction's wharves and storehouses in East Boston, receipts, correspondence, and statements on the condition of the steamer Wide Awake.
Papers of the Boston and Worcester Railroad, 1865-1866, include four letters and the decision of the Suffolk Supreme Court in the case of Charles Darling versus The Boston and Worcester Railroad.
For additional information on Massachusetts railroads of this period see: Francis B. C. Bradlee, The Lowell Railroad (Salem, 1918) and Boston & Maine R. R. (Salem, 1921).
Business; Railroads -- Massachusetts; Massachusetts -- Industries; New England; Darling, Charles; Jackson, P. T. (Patrick Tracy), 1780-1847; Nichols, R. R.; Sprague, Peleg, 1793-1880; Stark, George; Storrow, Charles S. (Charles Storer), 1809-1904; Boston and Albany Railroad Co; Boston and Lowell Railroad Corporation; Boston and Maine Railroad; Boston and Worcester Railroad Corporation; Grand Junction Railroad and Depot Co; Nashua and Lowell Railroad Corporation; New York Central Railroad Company; Wide Awake (Steamer)
- Inventory
  - Boston and Albany Railroad
    - Correspondence, 1828 May 1 - 1902 July 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Financial papers, 1859 July 1 - June 25, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Legal papers, 1828 May 26, 1828 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Steamboat schedules, 1827, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Map of route by the Islip, [1828] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Survey of Lebanon Hill, [1828] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Boston and Lowell Railroad
    - Correspondence, 1858 February 23 - 1875 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Financial papers, 1860 May 1 - 1875 August 1, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Legal papers, 1831 March 10 - 1880 November 9 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Printed matter, 1869 May 19 - 1872 March 28, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Stockholders' proxies and voting records, 1878 January 8 - 1882 November 10, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Papers concerning Lechmers Point Flats, 1822 - 1832 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      General
      See also: box 2, folder 33
  - Boston and Lowell Railroad and Boston and Maine Railroad
    - Act of the Legislature relating to the flats between Charles and Millers Rivers, 1845 March 25 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Boston and Lowell Railroad and Nashua and Lowell Railroad
    - Miscellaneous records, 1860 January 24 - 1876 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Boston, Lowell and Nashua Railroad
    - Miscellaneous records, 1863 April 25 - 1871 January 4 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Boston and Worcester Railroad
    - Miscellaneous records, 1865 October 4 - 1866 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Concord Railroad
    - Deed, 1843 November 13 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Grand Junction Railroad and Depot Co.
    - Correspondence, 1865 October 7 - 1867 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Papers concerning steamer, 1859 July 22 - 1868 June 5 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous records, 1859 October 11 - 1867 September 28 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous records, 1868 January 6 - 1870 January 7 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous records, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Nashua & Lowell Railroad vs. Boston & Lowell Railroad
    - Briefs, testimony, etc., 1839 March 1 - April 3-8, b.d. (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - Copy of indenture between the proprieters of the Canal bridge and Patrick Jackson, 1832 April 14 (Box 2)
  - Plan of Grand Junction wharves and store houses, East Boston, 1866 January 1 (Box 2)